At every stage of our lives
في كل مرحلة من حياتنا
we make decisions that will profoundly influence
نتخذ قرارات ستؤثر بشكل عميق
the lives of the people we're going to become,
على حياة الشخص الذي نتحول إليه،
and then when we become those people,
ثم عندما نصبح هذا الشخص،
we're not always thrilled with the decisions we made.
في بعض الأحيان قد لا نكون موفقين في هذه القرارات.
So young people pay good money
فيدفع الشباب أموالًا كثيرة
to get tattoos removed that teenagers
ليتخلصوا من هذا الوشم الذي دفع المراهقين
paid good money to get.
الكثير من الأموال ليحصلوا عليه.
Middle-aged people rushed to divorce people
يستعجل متوسطو العمر في أخذ قرار الطلاق
who young adults rushed to marry.
ويستعجل الشباب للزواج.
Older adults work hard to lose
يعمل البالغون الأكبر سنا بشدّة ليخسروا
what middle-aged adults worked hard to gain.
ما عمل متوسطو العمر من أجل كسبه.
On and on and on.
باستمرار.
The question is, as a psychologist, that fascinates me is,
أنا كعالم نفس، السؤال الذي يثير اهتمامي هو،
why do we make decisions
لماذا نتخذ قرارات
that our future selves so often regret?
دائمًا نندم عليها في المستقبل؟
Now, I think one of the reasons --
الآن، أعتقد أن إحدى الأسباب-
I'll try to convince you today —
التي سوف أحاول إقناعك بها اليوم-
is that we have a fundamental misconception
أنه عندنا فكرة خاطئة
about the power of time.
عن أهمية الوقت.
Every one of you knows that the rate of change
كلكم تعرفون أن معدل التغير
slows over the human lifespan,
يتباطأ خلال عمر الإنسان،
that your children seem to change by the minute
فتلاحظون أن أطفالكم يتغيرون في غضون دقائق
but your parents seem to change by the year.
ولكن آباءكم يتغيرون خلال السنة.
But what is the name of this magical point in life
ولكن ما إسم هذه النقطة الىساحرة في حياتنا
where change suddenly goes
عندما يتحول فجأة التغيير
from a gallop to a crawl?
من سرعة كبيرة إلى بطء شديد؟
Is it old age? The answer, it turns out,
هل هو عمر الشيخوخة؟ تبين أن الإجابة
for most people, is now,
بالنسبة لمعظم الناس، أن هذا الوقت هو حاليا،
wherever now happens to be.
وحيثما يحدث الآن.
What I want to convince you today
الشيء الذي أريد إقناعك به اليوم
is that all of us are walking around with an illusion,
هو أنه كلنا مخدوعون بوهم،
an illusion that history, our personal history,
توهمنا أن التاريخ، تاريخنا الشخصي بالتحديد،
has just come to an end,
قد وصل إلى نهاية،
that we have just recently become
وأننا أصبحنا مؤخرًا
the people that we were always meant to be
الأشخاص الذين كنا دائما نطمح لأن نكونهم
and will be for the rest of our lives.
وسوف نكون كذلك لآخر عمرنا.
Let me give you some data to back up that claim.
دعوني أعطكم بعض المعلومات للإيضاح أكثر.
So here's a study of change in people's
هذه دراسة عن التغيير في
personal values over time.
قيم الإنسان الشخصية عبر الوقت.
Here's three values.
هنا توجد ثلاثة معايير.
Everybody here holds all of them,
الجميع هنا يحملها جميعا،
but you probably know that as you grow,
ولكنك تعلم على الأرجح أنه عندما تكبر،
as you age, the balance of these values shifts.
وتتقدم في العمر، فإن هذه المعايير تختلف.
So how does it do so?
ولكن كيف تفعل ذلك؟
Well, we asked thousands of people.
عندما سألنا الآلاف من الناس.
We asked half of them to predict for us
طلبنا من نصف هؤلاء الناس أن يتنبؤوا لنا
how much their values would change in the next 10 years,
بمقدار ما يمكن أن يتغير من قيمهم خلال العشر سنوات القادمة،
and the others to tell us
وطلبنا من النصف الآخرأن يقول لنا،
how much their values had changed in the last 10 years.
بمقدار تغير قيمهم الفعلي خلال العشر سنوات الأخيرة،
And this enabled us to do a really interesting kind of analysis,
وهذا أعطانا فرصة لأن نحصل على تحليل مثير للاهتمام
because it allowed us to compare the predictions
لأنه سمح لنا بأن نقارن تنبؤات
of people, say, 18 years old,
الناس، دعنا نقل، ذوي 18 سنة،
to the reports of people who were 28,
مع ذوي 28 سنة،
and to do that kind of analysis throughout the lifespan.
وهذا النوع من التحاليل طوال دورة الحياة.
Here's what we found.
هذا ما حصلنا عليه.
First of all, you are right,
أولًا، أنت محق،
change does slow down as we age,
التغيير يتباطأ كلما كبرنا في العمر،
but second, you're wrong,
ولكن ثانيًا، أنت مخطئ،
because it doesn't slow nearly as much as we think.
لأنه لا يتباطأ بقدر ما نحن نعتقد.
At every age, from 18 to 68 in our data set,
في كل عمر، من 18 إلى 68 في مجموعة بيناتنا،
people vastly underestimated how much change
يقلل الناس من تقدير حجم التغيير بشكل كبير
they would experience over the next 10 years.
والذي سيختبرونه خلال ال10 سنوات القادمة.
We call this the "end of history" illusion.
نحن نسمي هذا بوهم "نهاية تاريخ".
To give you an idea of the magnitude of this effect,
لإعطاءك فكرة عن حجم هذا التأثير،
you can connect these two lines,
يمكنك التوصيل بين هذين الخطين،
and what you see here is that 18-year-olds
وما تراه هنا أن من يبلغ 18 سنة
anticipate changing only as much
يتوقع التغيير بقدر ما
as 50-year-olds actually do.
يتوقع البالغ من العمر 50 عامًا.
Now it's not just values. It's all sorts of other things.
هذه ليست فقط قيم، بل إنها بعض من كل شيء.
For example, personality.
مثلًا، الشخصية.
Many of you know that psychologists now claim
الكثير منكم يعلمون أن علماء النفس الآن يرجحون
that there are five fundamental dimensions of personality:
أن هناك 5 أبعد أساسية للشخصية:
neuroticism, openness to experience,
العصابية، الانفتاح على التجربة،
agreeableness, extraversion, and conscientiousness.
القبول، الانبساط، والضمير.
Again, we asked people how much they expected
مرة أخرى، سألنا الناس كم يتوقعون
to change over the next 10 years,
أن يتغيروا في خلال العشر سنوات القادمة،
and also how much they had changed over the last 10 years,
وأيضًا كم تغيرو خلال آخر 10 سنوات،
and what we found,
ما وجدناه،
well, you're going to get used to seeing this diagram over and over,
ستقوم بالتعود على رؤية هذا الرسم البياني تكرارا،
because once again the rate of change
لأنه مرة أخرى نسبة التغيير
does slow as we age,
تتغير كلما نتقدم في العمر،
but at every age, people underestimate
ولكن في كل عمر، الناس يقللون
how much their personalities will change
من قدر التغيير في شخصياتهم
in the next decade.
في العقد الموالي.
And it isn't just ephemeral things
ولكنها ليست فقط أشياء عابرة
like values and personality.
كالقيم والشخصية.
You can ask people about their likes and dislikes,
يمكنك أن تسأل الناس عما يحبون وما لا يحبون،
their basic preferences.
مفضلاتهم الأساسية.
For example, name your best friend,
مثلًا، أذكر أسم صديقك المفضل،
your favorite kind of vacation,
أفضل طريقة لقضاء إجازتك،
what's your favorite hobby,
ما هي هوايتك المفضلة،
what's your favorite kind of music.
ما هو أفضل نوع موسيقي بالنسبة لك.
People can name these things.
يمكن للناس ذكر هذه الأشياء.
We ask half of them to tell us,
نطلب من نصفهم أن يقولو لنا،
"Do you think that that will change over the next 10 years?"
"هل تعتقد أن هذا سوف يتغير خلال ال10 سنوات القادمة؟"
and half of them to tell us,
والنصف الآخر نسألهم،
"Did that change over the last 10 years?"
"هل تغير هذا خلال آخر 10 سنوات؟"
And what we find, well, you've seen it twice now,
وما وجدنا، أنت رأيته مرتيين لحد الآن،
and here it is again:
وها هو مجددًا:
people predict that the friend they have now
الناس تتنبأ أن صديقهم اليوم
is the friend they'll have in 10 years,
هو نفس الصديق الذي يكون في حياتهم في ال10 سنوات القادمة
the vacation they most enjoy now is the one
الإجازة التي يستمتعون بها الآن هي نفسها
they'll enjoy in 10 years,
التي سيستمتعون بها بعد 10 سنوات،
and yet, people who are 10 years older all say,
على الرغم من أن الأشخاص الأكبر ب-10 أعوام كلهم يقولون،
"Eh, you know, that's really changed."
"تعلمون، هذا الواقع تغير بالفعل."
Does any of this matter?
هل كل هذا شيء يهم؟
Is this just a form of mis-prediction that doesn't have consequences?
هل كل هذا نوع من سوء التوقع الذي لا يحمل عواقب؟
No, it matters quite a bit, and I'll give you an example of why.
بلى، إنه يهم قليلًا، وسأعطيكم مثالًا عن السبب.
It bedevils our decision-making in important ways.
إنه يشوش على اتخاذ القرار بأساليب مهمة.
Bring to mind right now for yourself
فكر الآن في
your favorite musician today
الموسيقي المفضل لديك اليوم
and your favorite musician 10 years ago.
والموسيقي التي كانت مفضلة لديك قبل 10 سنوات.
I put mine up on the screen to help you along.
وضعت لكم المفضلين لدي على الشاشة لمساعدتكم.
Now we asked people
الآن سألنا الناس
to predict for us, to tell us
ليتوقعوا لنا، ويقولوا لنا
how much money they would pay right now
كم من الأموال سينفقونها حاليًا
to see their current favorite musician
ليروا الموسيقي المفضل لديهم
perform in concert 10 years from now,
يؤدي في حفل بعد 10 سنوات من اليوم،
and on average, people said they would pay
وفي المتوسط، الناس قالوا أنهم سيدفعون
129 dollars for that ticket.
129 دولار للتذكرة.
And yet, when we asked them how much they would pay
ومع ذلك، حين سألناهم كم سيدفعون
to see the person who was their favorite
ليروا الشخص الذي كان مفضلا
10 years ago perform today,
لديهم قبل 10 سنوات في عرض أداء اليوم،
they say only 80 dollars.
قالوا فقط 80 دولار.
Now, in a perfectly rational world,
الآن، في عالم عقلاني كامل،
these should be the same number,
من المفروض أن يكون الرقمان متساويان،
but we overpay for the opportunity
ولكننا ندفع المزيد من أجل الفرصة
to indulge our current preferences
لكي نشبع رغبتنا في الأفضليات الحالية
because we overestimate their stability.
لأننا نبالغ في تقدير دوامها.
Why does this happen? We're not entirely sure,
لماذا يحدث ذلك؟ لسنا متأكدين كليًا،
but it probably has to do
ولكن من المحتمل أن تكون
with the ease of remembering
بسهولة التذكر
versus the difficulty of imagining.
مقابل صعوبة التخيل.
Most of us can remember who we were 10 years ago,
الكثير منا يتذكر كيف كان منذ 10 سنوات،
but we find it hard to imagine who we're going to be,
ولكن يصعب علينا أن نتخيل كيف سنكون،
and then we mistakenly think that because it's hard to imagine,
ولكننا نخطئ في التفكير في ذلك لأنه صعب علينا أن نتخيل،
it's not likely to happen.
أنه لا يحتمل أن يحدث.
Sorry, when people say "I can't imagine that,"
آسف، عندما يقول الناس "لا استطيع أن أتخيل ذلك،"
they're usually talking about their own lack of imagination,
إنهم عادةً يتكلمون عن عدم القدرة على التخيل،
and not about the unlikelihood
وليس عن استبعاد
of the event that they're describing.
الحدث الذي يحاولون وصفه.
The bottom line is, time is a powerful force.
خلاصة القول، الوقت قوة قديرة.
It transforms our preferences.
إنه يغير مفضلاتنا.
It reshapes our values.
إنه يعيد تشكيل قيمنا.
It alters our personalities.
إنه يغير شخصيتنا.
We seem to appreciate this fact,
يبدو أننا نقدر هذه الواقعة،
but only in retrospect.
ولكن فقط في استعادة الأحداث الماضية.
Only when we look backwards do we realize
فقط عندما ننظر إلى الخلف نبدأ في ملاحظة
how much change happens in a decade.
كم من التغيير يحدث عبر السنين.
It's as if, for most of us,
إنه كما لو أنه، بالنسبة لمعظمنا،
the present is a magic time.
الحاضر هو وقت ساحر.
It's a watershed on the timeline.
إنه نقطة تحول في جدول زمني.
It's the moment at which we finally
إنها اللحظة التي في نهايتها
become ourselves.
نصبح أنفسنا.
Human beings are works in progress
البشر يعملون في التقدم المحرز
that mistakenly think they're finished.
وعن طريق التفكير الخاطئ يعتقدون أنهم قد انتهوا.
The person you are right now
الشخص الذي هو أنت الآن
is as transient, as fleeting and as temporary
هو فقط عابر، كلحظة سريعة ومؤقتة
as all the people you've ever been.
مثلما كنت في أي وقت مضى.
The one constant in our life is change.
الشيء الوحيد الثابت في حياتنا هو التغيير.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)